Does soda, energy drinks, and the like,
the sugar sweetened kind, raise your
risk of dying from colurectal cancer? As
I've been asked in the past, is that
also the case for non sugarsw sweetened
soda like diet soda? The answer is yes
to the first question, but with several
layers of context and nuance, because
the real answer may not affect some at
all and be very important for others. I
released an analysis a while back
looking at the mechanistic argument for
how soda, the sugar sweetened kind,
causes colurectal cancer to be more
aggressive and spread more. And while I
did touch on the evidence in humans,
there's much more to be said. So, I
pulled multiple large studies
investigating this very topic, which
amounted to over 300,000 people being
studied to find out if soda raises our
risk of cancer overall. if those with
colorectile cancer are more likely to
die and if you recover from colorectal
cancer are you more likely to develop it
again. These are three important
distinguishing points because each
question addresses different populations
of people. So in reverse order when we
want to know if colorectile cancer is
more likely to lead to death or come
back when we consume soda we have to
look at people who have colorectal
cancer as well as people who have had
the cancer removed and are trying to
keep it at bay. That's what we see here
when we track people over a median seven
years after their cancer has been
removed and then we see how many people
experience a return of their cancer. We
can stratify based on the amount of
sugar sweetened beverage intake. In
doing so, along with controlling for
many factors, so obvious influencing
factors, there's 75% increased risk of
cancer recurrence. That means in simpler
terms, colurectal cancer is more likely
to return when we consume sugarsw
sweetened beverages, soda being the
dominant one. Now when taking things a
step further when we look at people
still dealing with present colctal
cancer the study found no initial
relationship between se sweetened
beverages again that's dominantly soda
and increased risk of colctal cancer
mortality. So is it a risk of recurrence
but doesn't make the cancer worse after
that point? Well not quite. And here we
may be touching on one of those nuances
that I alluded to in the mechanisms that
we discussed in the previous analysis. I
mentioned a more aggressive cancer from
exposure to these sugars. So glucose and
fructose, the same ones found in sugar
sweetened beverages. If that's sucrose
sweetened or high fructose corn syrup
sweetened. Well, in this study that
we're going over, the researchers point
out that there's no relationship between
these sweetened drinks and colurectal
cancer mortality when looking at all the
data. But when segmenting based on
deaths in the first 5 years or after 5
years, there was a detected increase in
the risk of death from colurectal cancer
in the first 5 years. So what could this
mean? While the researchers mention a
critical biological window where a
person could be recovering from a
treatment or experiencing undetected
metastasis, so spreading of the cancer,
which could be fueled by a greater
intake in sugar beverages. Now, this
would also play into the idea that this
particular cancer when exposed to sugar
in this context spreads more. So this
could be a signal that sugar sweetened
beverages make colorectal cancer
progress more quickly and more deadly.
It could also be that some people have
more localized cancer, so less severe
cancer, or that only particular colctal
cancers are prone to supercharging their
aggression, creating this time scale
difference. The takeaway here being that
colorectal cancer mortality risk is
likely to be increased when consuming
sugarsweetened beverages. Again, soda
being the dominant. If a person has
colorectal cancer, but what about most
of you? Could there be an increased risk
of colctal cancer from consuming soda?
Does it matter if it's sweetened or
sugar-free? Well, when looking at
studies including almost 200,000
participants, the answer to the first
question might be no. No link was
detected for sweetened beverages, but
oddly enough, they did find a
relationship with total sugar
consumption. However, the study has some
major limitations. For example, while
the study ran for an average of 19
years, measurements were only taken once
at the beginning of the study. So, as
the study progresses, the data is highly
likely to become more and more outdated.
The best we can do is to say that
there's an association to baseline data
collected nearly 20 years ago.
Fortunately, there are better studies
investigating the same issue. These
studies, which use data collected from a
mere 100,000 participants, but lasted
much longer, 10 to 20 years longer, as
well as tracked people's metrics like
dietary intake changes and lifestyle
changes and more every 2 to four years,
which offer much more quality data.
Interestingly, when we look at cancer
mortality in this data set, we do see a
step-wise relationship. The yellow line
at the bottom indicates a neutral
relationship and anything north of that
indicates a harmful relationship. So,
greater cancer mortality. At most
intakes, there's clearly increased risk.
This is repeated in more specialized
populations when using a similar data
set as well. though this study focused
on cancer occurrence showing a 16%
increased risk at the highest intakes.
So not quite as straightforward
considering this study looked at overall
cancer mortality and the other two were
focused on colorectal cancer. In
addition, we don't know if the deaths
happened in people with colurectal
cancer since the study didn't control
for that at the beginning. It only
controlled for family history of cancer.
Still, this other study looking at
cancer occurrence did control for people
who had endoscopy screening for fear of
colon cancer as well as a family history
of colon cancer. And it still found a
relationship in people who didn't have
either. This all comes together to
create a bit trickier takeaway. I'd
cautiously suggest that there's at least
a signal between soda, again that's the
primary sugarsw sweetened beverage
included, and colurectal cancer
occurrence risk. Though I would like to
see more direct data. I'll explain more
of that in just a bit. Now, we've been
heavily focused on these sugar-filled
drinks, but many people use the
alternative for soda pop. They use
sugar-free options like those with
artificial sweeteners or other
non-nutritive sweeteners, essentially
diet soda. So, do we see the same
relationship there? I'm going to make
quick work of that in just a second. But
if you're looking to learn about a bit
about other types of cancer or if uh
fruit juices have the same warnings or
if substituting for other drinks like
milk, coffee, and others might change
the risk and more, then check out my
full analysis. It's an extended video of
the one that you're watching. It's
adree. It comes with an article, one
paragraph summary of the most important
takeaways. And that's consistent across
all my analyses, multiple per week on
average that release for the Physionic
Insiders, where the land of scientific
wonder expands into a wonderland of
mirths and high-fives.
That last part may or may not be true,
but you do get access to all my work,
plus a private podcast, live sessions,
and more. The link to join the insiders
is in the description. I hope to see you
there. Diet soda across every single
study because most looked at it does
not show any relationship with
colurectal cancer. That's like an
episode of uh of my diet soda. You are
not the father of this cancer.
Okay, I would make that more complex,
but that's really it. And it's not a
surprise considering the mechanisms that
were explained in my previous work. I'll
link it for you if you're interested.
The mechanism solely revolved around
glucose and fructose, neither of which
are found in diet soda. Now, of course,
there could be other mechanisms, but as
it stands, we don't have any evidence
that diet soda increases the risk of
developing or dying from colurectal
cancer. So, in short, don't worry about
diet soda in relation to colurectal or
colon cancer. Now, two important things
that you should know. One, almost all of
these studies looked at body weight. You
know, since drinking sugary drinks can
promote weight gain and weight gain and
especially obesity can cause cancer,
these results were still present even
when weight was accounted for. So, no,
it is not the obesity causing this
relationship. There is a maintained
association even when controlling for
that major factor. Two, the dose makes
the poison. I said this last time, but
the amount of sweetened beverage matters
a lot. In fact, across the studies, a
rough estimate where risk is
consistently identified is around two
sodas a day. Some studies showed it with
a bit less while others didn't, and some
looked at a bit more. But they all hover
around two 240ml
drinks. This also means that well while
not exactly a health treat having a soda
every now and again isn't going to
suddenly churn up colurectal cancer.
It's a consistent intake too. Okay, that
was a lot. Maybe we should take a breath
before we put all this together into
some actionable takeaways and go over
how to think about all this.
Everything considered, here's where we
land. I think we have strong enough
evidence including the mechanistic data
that if you have colarctal cancer
consider avoiding sugarsw sweetened soda
and possibly most sugar sweetened
drinks. If you have had colurectal
cancer and you want to give yourself the
best chance of not allowing it to come
back do the same. Avoid the sodas. If
you do not have colctal cancer and are
otherwise healthy the certainty in the
evidence diminishes. There are signals
there that it's still a colctal cancer
risk, but it is not as certain as the
previous scenarios. So maybe consider
reducing consumption, but keep in mind
that once in a while treats is probably
pretty benign. More direct data is
definitely needed. So if you drink diet
non-s sugar soda, there is no identified
colctal cancer risk. So you're probably
fine. If you'd like to know exactly how
sugar accelerates colurectal cancer,
actually gets into the cancer cells and
understand what makes them supercharge
their growth, then check out my initial
analysis right here. Thanks for tuning
in. Have a great sugar-free day. I'll
speak with you soon.